Finding Aid for Senate (University of Michigan) records, 1880-1995
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Senate (University of Michigan) records 1880-1995 1906-1987
University of Michigan. Senate.
87309 Bimu B31a 2
Minutes,1880-1984; correspondence, 1910-1924, concerning the Senate Committee on Student Affairs, including material on student organizations, clubs, and fraternities; papers, 1959-1962, concerning the Senate Advisory Committee's sub-committee on the aims of the University; Senate memorials, 1951-1953; history of the University Senate by Louis Hopkins; minutes, Oct. 1911-Oct. 1916, of the Senate Council; papers, 1906-1916, of the Senate Council, including history
5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was transferred by the University Senate (donor no. 234 ).
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The records are open to research.
The University Senate is a political institution made up of all members of the university faculty. It serves as a forum for faculty opinion on issues affecting the campus, and has also functioned as a social organization for professors. The university regents first officially recognized the University Senate in March, 1859, although the faculty may have met as a body prior to that date. The influence of the Senate was probably greatest during the 19th Century. In that era, faculty members played a strong role in the administration of the university, both through the formal meetings of the Senate and through less formal consultation with the university president.
In the early 20th century, the nature of university governance began to change. Faculty participation in policy formation declined as decisions were increasingly made by a growing class of professional administrators. The administrative reorganization of 1906-07 hinted at the beginning of this change. At that time, the powers of the University Senate were transferred to a smaller executive body, the Senate Council, which balanced representatives of the administration and those of the faculty. Despite this change, the division between faculty and administrators remained indistinct at this stage. Members of the faculty continued to have a strong role in administrative decision making and most administrators were faculty members who continued to teach classes. Nevertheless, the structure of the new Senate Council recognized a growing gap between the duties of faculty and administrators.
In 1931, the Senate transferred all its power to a new organization, the University Council, which replaced the Senate Council. The University Council was composed of administration officials and elected faculty members from each school and department. Its creation reflected the continued growth of the administration, and represented another attempt to balance representation between faculty and administrators. In 1937, the unmanageable size of the University Council led to the creation of a smaller executive body, the Senate Advisory Committee on University Affairs (SACUA). SACUA consisted of some members elected by the Senate and others chosen by the Dean's Conference. SACUA members represented the Senate in the University Council and reported to the Senate. In 1940, the importance of SACUA was diminished with the creation of another executive governing body, the Advisory Board on University Policies. This new body was appointed by the Board of Regents, and therefore weakened faculty control over university governance. In 1948, University Council had ceded most of its functions to these smaller executive bodies and was dissolved. The same year, SACUA was restructured to serve as an executive body of the Senate, with its members elected at-large by the Senate.
In 1965, the University Senate again reorganized faculty governance by creating a body called the Senate Assembly. The new body consisted of sixty-five members elected to represent the various colleges and schools of the university. The Assembly served as the legislative arm of the Senate and elected the members of SACUA.
Researchers interested in the nature of faculty governance might wish to consult Nicholas Steneck's 1991 SACUA report Faculty Governance at the University of Michigan: Principles, History, and Practice, which is in the holdings of the Bentley Historical Library (Call number: Fimu B31a.3 S 825).
The record group consists of eight series: Student Affairs, Committee Material, Memorials, Historical, Senate Council, Minutes, Correspondence and Elections, and Senate Assembly Material. Researchers should note that the Bentley Historical Library also holds a separate record group, University of Michigan Senate Advisory Committee on University Affairs (SACUA) which contains related material.
Subjects:
Teacher participation in administration--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Committee on Student Affairs.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Senate Council.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.; Greek letter societies--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Societies and clubs.; University of Michigan. Senate. Advisory Committee on University Affairs.; University of Michigan--History.
Contributors:
Hopkins, Louis Allen.
- Student Affairs
  The Student Affairs series consists of correspondence, minutes, and petitions from 1910 to 1924 dealing with student activities and organizations. Subjects include fraternities, sororities, other student social clubs, honor societies, and student dances.
  - Senate Committee on Student Affairs (Box 1)
    - Annual Reports 1915-1919, 1930 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1910-1924, 11 folders (Box 1)
    - Minutes 1902-1943, 4 volumes (Box 1)
    - Minutes 1943-1952, 3 volumes (Box 1a)
    - Petitions on Reinstatement of the Junior Hop 1913-1915 (Box 1a)
- Committee Material
  The Committee Material series consists of correspondence and minutes from 1902 to 1962 relating to Senate or SACUA committees. The series includes material on the selection of the university's official colors.
  - Committee on Non-Athletic Organizations 1902-1917 (Box 1a)
  - Reception Committee 1908-1914 (Box 1a)
  - Senate Committee to Choose Official School Colors
    - Correspondence 1912 (Box 1a)
    - Samples of Colors from University Diplomas 1859-1912 (Box 1a)
  - Committee of the Senate on University Affairs 1929-1931 (Box 1a)
  - Senate Advisory Committee's Subcommittee on the Aims of the University 1959-1962, 4 folders (Box 1a)
  - Papers Concerning the Senate; (mostly committee material) 1943-1951, 3 folders (Box 2)
- Memorials
  The Memorials series is made up of Senate memorials to deceased professors. The memorials often contain considerable biographical information about their subjects.
  - Claude Halsted Van Tyne 1930 (Box 2)
  - Joseph Markley 1931 (Box 2)
  - Robert Bunker 1931 (Box 2)
  - Horace La Feyette Wilgus 1935 (Box 2)
  - Memorials 1951-1953
    - A-F (Box 2)
      (in one folder)
      - Randolph G. Adams
      - Edwin Myron Baker
      - George Harolde Belote
      - Raúl Benedicto
      - Samuel Lawrence Bigelow
      - James A. Bruce
      - Paul Narciss Bukovksy
      - William Henry Butts
      - Arthur Graves Canfield
      - Palmer Christian
      - George C. Cone
      - Mortimer Edwyn Cooley
      - David Murray Cowie
      - Heber Doust Curtis
      - Earle Dow
      - Joseph Horace Drake
      - Charles Edmunds
      - Herbert Emerson
      - John Edward Emswiler
      - Charles Fischer
      - Richard Corbin Fuller
    - G-M (Box 2)
      - Clifford Glover
      - Edwin C. Goddard
      - Moses Gomberg
      - Louis Hall
      - Joseph Ralston Hayden
      - William D. Henderson
      - Henry Harold Higbie
      - Juva N. Higbee
      - Wilbert B. Hinsdale
      - Abram A. James
      - John Johnstone
      - Myra Beach Jordan
      - Thomas Albert Knott
      - Norman Kretzschmar
      - Moritz Levi
      - David Martin Lichty
      - Joseph Newhall Lincoln
      - Selma A. Lindell
      - Felix Carlos Lopez
      - George A. May
      - Edwin Wilkinson Miller
      - George R. Moore
      - Roger L. Morrison
    - O-Z (Box 2)
      - David Owen
      - Albert Becker Peck
      - Reuben Peterson
      - Jesse Siddall Reeves
      - Jacob Ellsworth Reighard
      - Eugene Etienne Rovillain
      - Will Carl Rufus
      - Alviso B. Stevens
      - Morris Palmer Tilley
      - Elmer Rolland Townsley
      - Allen Whitney
      - Howard Marshall Wight
      - Norman Asa Wood
      - Clarence Stone Yoakum
      - Fielding Harris Yost
      - William Hoyt Worrell
      - Correspondence re memorials
- Historical
  The Historical series consists of a brief history of the Senate and a folder of material outlining Senate minutes and regents meetings.
  - "History of the University Senate," Manuscript by Louis Hopkins (Box 2)
  - Outline of Senate Minutes 1881-1931 and Outline of Regents Meetings, 1837-1864 (Box 2)
- Senate Council
  The Senate Council series consists of materials from 1906 to 1931 documenting the activities of the Senate Council. The Senate Council served as the executive board of the Senate, and its minutes, like those of the larger Senate, deal with a wide variety of subjects relating to university governance. The series also contains Senate Council papers consisting of correspondence and reports, and a brief history of the Senate Council.
  - Minutes 1906-1931, 3 volumes (Box 2)
  - Papers 1906-1916, 13 folders
    - 1906-1911 (Box 2)
    - 1906-1911 (Box 3)
  - History of the Senate Council 1906-1911, 1912-1916 (Box 3)
- Minutes
  The Minutes series consists of Senate minutes, mostly in bound volumes, from 1880 to 1984. The minutes include committee reports, memorials, and resolutions. The minutes deal with a wide range of subjects, including student athletics, faculty compensation, student social life, and educational policy. The earlier meetings tend to contain more material relating to student life, while the later volumes contain more material about the relationship between the faculty and the administration. The volumes covering the years 1953-54 include a considerable amount of material relating to the investigation, censure and dismissal of professors accused of communist subversion.
  - 1880-1903 (labeled "Records") (Box 3)
  - 1904-1907 (labeled "Records") (Box 3)
  - 1907-1922 (Box 3)
  - 1922-1929 (Box 3)
  - 1929-1943 (Box 3)
  - 1943-1948 (Box 3)
  - 1948-1949 (Box 3)
  - 1950-1953 (Box 3)
  - 1953-1955 (Box 4)
  - 1955-1958 (Box 4)
  - 1958-1961 (Box 4)
  - 1961-1965 (Box 4)
    (includes Senate Assembly Minutes)
  - 1965-1970 (Box 4)
  - 1970-1975 (Box 4)
  - 1970-1979 (Box 5)
  - 1980-1984 (Box 5)
- Correspondence and Elections
  The Correspondence and Elections series consists of Senate correspondence and documents relating to Senate elections of SACUA members from 1958 to 1978, bound in one volume.
  - Senate Correspondence 1958-1978 Elections to SACUA, 1955-1965 (Box 5)
    (bound in a single volume)
- Senate Assembly 1965-1995 (Box 5)
  The Senate Assembly series consists of material relating to that body from 1965 to 1995. Researchers interested in subcommittees of the Senate Assembly should refer to the separate University of Michigan Senate Advisory Committee on University Affairs (SACUA) holdings.
  - Correspondence 1965-1971 (Box 5)
  - Agendas and Minutes 1966-1970 (Box 5)
  - Agendas
    - 1988, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1994-1995 (Box 5)
  - Minutes
    - 1972-1982 (Box 5)
    - 1984-1987 (Box 5)
    - 1993-1995 (Box 5)
  - Membership of Senate Assembly 1993-1995 (Box 5)
  - President's Retreat 1994 (Box 5)
  - Report on Nomination and Election to Senate Assembly 1973 (Box 5)
  - Rules of Senate Assembly and SACUA 1967-1975 (Box 5)